We had um $2 million in cash in the van
with us in two duffel bags and my
colleague said, "What would possess you
to cheat the CIA out of 20 bucks? If
you're going to steal, steal millions."
And we looked at each other and laughed.
Yeah. Be a little hard to pass a
polygraph on that, right?
[Music]
Today I am honored to welcome to the Dr.
Phil podcast a true patriot,
whistleblower and author John Keryaku.
Now John is a former CIA
counterterrorism officer and a senior
investigator for the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee and played a key
role in counterterrorism in the
aftermath of 9/11 and beyond. John felt
compelled to expose some practices being
employed by the CIA that he just did not
feel morally comfortable with. We're
talking about things that he considered
to be outright torture. Such things as
water boarding, for example. Now, some
of these
disclosures I'm going to say led to
his
indictment, and I'm not sure that that's
exactly right. We'll let him describe
what he thinks led to his indictment.
There's what was said publicly that led
to his indictment and, you know, a lot
of things behind the scenes that may
have led to the indictment. We'll let
him talk about that in a minute. But the
indictment was by the Obama
administration and it was under the
Espionage Act. Now, that's a law
designed to punish spies. I don't think
anybody ever accused him of being a spy,
but nonetheless, that was the act that
was imposed. He served 23 months in
prison as a result of his attempts to
oppose the Bush administration's torture
program. Now, John is a best-selling
author of The Reluctant Spy and Doing
Time Like a Spy. John received the Joe
A. Callaway Award for civic courage and
continues to champion human rights and
transparency. Boy, transparency has
become a real important
issue in this day and time. Now, beyond
his career in intelligence and writing,
John continues to advocate for human
rights, transparency, and the ethical
treatment of whistleblowers like
himself. John, thank you so much for
joining me today.
Thank you so much for having me, Dr.
Phil. Such a pleasure for me. Well, you
have been a busy guy in your profession.
A couple of quotes that I want to
attribute to you, and you can own them
or not. I want to be sure I'm right. One
is you said I exposed the CIA and went
to prison for it. Is that something you
said? Uh it is. You said there are some
things we should not do even in the name
of national security. Is that something
you said? Indeed it is. All right. This
is something that you took very
seriously in your life. Why did you go
into the CIA? Were you recruited? I was
recruited in graduate school, but to
tell you the truth, I was only
considering uh jobs in public service.
I'm the grandson of four uh uh
grandparents who immigrated to this
country from Greece. And in our
household while I was growing up, uh it
was instilled in all of us really that
that we owed this country such a great
debt of thanks for giving us a new life
in this wonderful country that we needed
to pay that debt back. And so my parents
were elementary school teachers in the
public school system and they instilled
in us the notion that we should go into
public service as well. So, you went
into public service, but you didn't sit
around in the sandbox as a kid
envisioning yourself being a CIA agent.
Actually, I did uh when I was nine, I
told my parents that I wanted to be a
spy when I grew up. And they bought me
uh walkietalkies for for Christmas that
year. I remember. Yeah. And then when I
was 16, I said specifically, I I
remember telling my father that not only
did I want to be a spy, but I wanted to
be a spy in the Middle East. And so I um
I went to George Washington University
and got a an undergraduate degree in
Middle Eastern studies. Uh, I stayed at
GW for a master's degree in legislative
affairs, but with a concentration in
foreign policy analysis, thinking if I
can't get into the CIA, I'll go to
Capitol Hill or I'll go to the foreign
service. And then, as it turned out, my
graduate school advisor
uh, who gave me an A on a paper, it was
a psychology exam, asked me to, he wrote
in the in the margin of the paper,
please see me after class. So I went to
see him and he said, 'Look, I'm not
really a professor here. I'm a CIA
officer undercover as a professor here
and I'm looking for people who might fit
into the CIA's culture. Would you like
to be a CIA officer? And I jumped at the
chance and the next thing I knew, I had
my right hand in the air and I was
swearing an oath to uphold the
Constitution.
Wow. So he was he was kind of taking a
chance because he was undercover. So, he
was actually Let's talk about that for a
minute because I have an
issue with some of what's going on in
the elite universities of the United
States right now. And I'm wondering if
we're sending our kids to get educated
or
indoctrinated. What do you say about
that?
Right. that is going to be a fight that
we are going to have to fight from here
on out. I will say that the way that I
was uh uh recruited into the CIA is no
longer legal. With passage in 1993 of
the Equal Employment Opportunity Act,
you can't do this old boy network. But
what they do now is they just do it out
in public. The CIA created this this uh
program called the Scholar and Residence
Program. So if you've done your 25 or 30
years, you're planning to retire,
they'll send you back to your alma mater
for two or three years, you can teach
some meaningless class like a friend of
mine went back to Indiana University and
taught uh espionage in Soviet literature
and uh and students will just go up to
him after class and say, "Hey, I'd love
to get into the CIA." And he makes a
recommendation. So rather than do it to
do it behind closed doors like they did
it with me, they just do it out in the
open now.
Okay. So we actually do have
professors in universities now that
aren't necessarily who they seem to be.
Correct.
They are actually operatives, CIA
operatives or maybe from other agencies
that are there to indoctrinate, to
recruit. What What are they there for?
Why are they in those roles? Oh, it's a
combination of the two. They're always
looking for people with hard foreign
languages or people who have an aptitude
for difficult foreign languages. They're
looking for people who are patriotic on
their face, patriotic, and if they think
that you can fit into that culture, and
it's it's deeper than just, you know,
fitting into the culture. I I've said uh
in many podcasts that a CIA psychiatrist
once told me that the CIA actively seeks
to hire people who have sociopathic
tendencies, not sociopaths. Because, of
course, sociopaths have no conscience.
They blow right through a polygraph
exam, but they're impossible to control.
People who have sociopathic tendencies
do have a conscience. They do react to
the polygraph, but at the same time,
they're happy to operate in these moral,
legal, and ethical gray areas. I I
remember when I was when I was going
through the interview process, um there
were four or five of us there and uh and
the instructor said, "Let's say you're a
CIA officer and you get a cable from
headquarters telling you to uh recruit
the Indonesian economic secretary
because you need some Indonesian
economic information." And you cultivate
this relationship for a year. you become
friends, your wives become friends, you
vacation together, but you you come to
realize that he's not recruitable. What
do you do? And a guy put his hand up in
the air and said, "Well, you double
down. You do it another 6 months." A
woman raised her hand and said, "Uh,
maybe you can work it through the
wives." And I'm looking around looking
at these people. I put my hand up and I
said, "You break into the embassy and
you steal it." And the instructor said,
"That's exactly what you do." Well, I
came to learn that's a sociopathic
tendency. Do you have sociopathic
tendencies? Probably. Uh, I was
perfectly happy to break into people's
homes or offices overseas and plant bugs
or plant cameras. I was perfectly happy
to convince people that I was their best
friend to the point where they were wi
willing to commit espionage for me or in
some cases treason because I believed we
were the good guys and I was doing this
uh for the safety and security of of
Americans and American installations.
And so I never gave it a second thought
beyond the fact that we were the good
guys.
Life is full of surprises and
emergencies often strike when we least
expect them. But preparation is key and
that's where Jace Casease comes in. With
Jace Casease, you'll have essential
emergency prescription medications right
at your fingertips, ready when you need
them most. Whether it's an unexpected
illness or a travel mishap, having the
right meds on hand can turn a potential
crisis into just a minor inconvenience.
Don't let the unexpected catch you off
guard. Jace Casease gives you peace of
mind so you can tackle life surprises
with
confidence. Be ready. Take charge today.
Head over to jace.com. That's
j.com. And when you check out, use the
code Phil, spelled P H I L, to get a
discount on your order and to have the
right meds on hand the moment you need
them. If you're a business owner, listen
up now. You will not want to miss this.
Outdated systems are costing you time,
money, and opportunity. Thousands of
companies have modernized with FYSI's AI
integration and solutions. FYSI
implements smart automation and
predictive insights that sharpen your
competitive edge. This is what separates
billiondoll companies from small
businesses. And FYSI can help you make
that leap. Don't wait. Get your free
$5,000 risk assessment now with promo
code Dr. Phil. That is promo code dr
phil l at
fysi.com/drfill or call
8008774000 today. That's code drill.
Visit
fysi.com/drill or call
8008774000 for your free $5,000 risk
assessment. So you say the CIA hires
people with sociopathic tendencies. And
you say sociopaths have concise answers
and pass polygraph tests. Sociopaths are
impossible to control. They slip through
the cracks because they have no
conscience. And they only hire
sociopathic narcissists. The CI
operatives look for narcissistic
individuals because they're so arrogant.
They conclude, of course, the CIA would
want to recruit me because I'm so
important that they cannot do their jobs
without me. Oh my goodness. You see that
every single day of your career. You are
surrounded by the smartest, the most
accomplished,
uh the the best educated, at least all
in their own minds people. Uh it it
becomes comical after a while. Yeah. You
actually don't see that so much in
analysis. It's in operations where
everybody wants to be James Bond. And in
some cases, they actually achieve that.
You know, there there is always a
handful of senior officers that all the
rest of us wanted to be like, people who
had many recruitments, people who had uh
multiple chief of station assignments.
That's that's what everybody was
aspiring to. And and you get it by what
they used to call, not jokingly,
shameless self-promotion. Yeah. Now,
were you that way? Is that why they
picked you? Was it languages? Why did
they pick you? Were you a sociopathic
narcissist? In retrospect, I I probably
had those sociopathic tendencies. But
they picked me. I I actually spent the
first half of my career in analysis.
They picked me
because because I had uh Arabic language
um and because I I was very serious
about academia. I was very serious about
analysis and study and I I was
fascinated by Arab culture and Arab
history. I read Arab poetry. I studied
Islam uh under one of the most important
uh Islamic scholars in the western
world. I I was just fascinated with that
culture and I wanted to live there and
really get to understand people and so I
went to the directorate of intelligence,
the analytic uh branch and succeeded not
necessarily because I was so great but
because I was really lucky. Just as I
got to a point where I felt like I knew
what I was doing, Iraq invaded Kuwait on
August the 2nd, 1990. I was the only
Iraq leadership analyst. And I remember
walking in that morning and saying uh to
my boss, "Big day ahead of us today."
And he said, "Don't take your jacket
off. We're going to the Oval Office." I
was 25 years old. And I walk in and it's
the president, the vice president, the
national security adviser, the CIA
director, my boss, and me. And we all
sit down. The president looks around and
he says, "Well, now what do we do?" And
then everybody turned and looked at me.
And I remember thinking to myself, my
friends from high school would never
believe it in a million years if I told
them what I was doing right now. So I I
got lucky there. You were more than just
lucky. Look, you received 10 exceptional
performance award. The sustained
superior performance award, the
counterterrorism service medal, the
state department's meritorious honor
award among others. What kind of things
did you do to earn those kind of
accolades? I found myself very often in
situations where you have to think
quickly, where bullets are flying, where
people's lives are at risk. And um and
there were a couple of there were a
couple of very difficult recruitments uh
that that I made. You know, in
retrospect, part of that was because I
was young and foolish. And you know,
when you're young, you think you're
going to live forever and you're
untouchable. And so, I would take risks
that today as a 60-year-old man, I I'm
appalled that I made a decision to take
some of these risks. Give me an example.
Um, I remember going into the heavily
communist anarchist neighborhood of
Athens, Greece to pitch a bonafide
terrorist. And I was the only member of
the team not wearing a bulletproof vest.
And my boss asked me, "Why in the world
did you not put your vest on?" I said,
"Because it shows underneath our shirts,
and I don't want to freak the guy out."
I said, 'I genuinely want to recruit
this guy. I don't want him to run away
and to be afraid or to see that we're
wearing vests and pull out a gun and
take a shot. I'm willing to I'm willing
to give it a chance. Besides, I had a
gun on my waist and a fanny pack. I had
another gun on my ankle in an ankle
holster. I thought, well, you know, if
I'm going to go down, I'm going to go
down shooting, but I'm going to give
this recruitment an actual chance. And I
recruited him. This was a a group that
no that the CIA had never infiltrated
before, but I took it slowly. I did the
research and uh and found success.
Right. And that's a chance you wouldn't
take today.
No, it's not a chance I would take
today. I kick myself. Well, you have
five children now, right? So, I have
five children, right? And I think they
would be quite upset with me. Yeah. You
look at it a little differently when you
have kids. They reward you for that kind
of thing. But you say that when you go
into the CIA, there is no class on
morality. They don't sit down and go
over ethics with you. They look for
results, not how you get
them. That's exactly right. And that was
something that bothered me for a very
long time. Although I never had to
really do anything about it until the
immediate aftermath of the 9/11 attacks.
That's when things changed. Not just for
me, but it changed for the agency. And
it changed in a big and permanent way.
They started playing a different kind of
ball. They started playing hard ball.
They started being more desperate to get
information. Is that the shift?
That's right. Let's cut to the chase.
Your savings could be in serious
trouble. When Elon Musk is out here
warning us to brace for temporary
hardship, you might want to listen. I
trust Preserve Gold to safeguard my
accounts, and I urge you to do the same.
They're the only precious metals company
I recommend. Are you going to sit back
and hope for the best or take control of
your financial future? Text Dr. Phil to
5050 to get your free precious metals
guide from Preserve Gold. With gold
prices recently breaking records and
analysts predicting this trend to
continue through 2025, you cannot afford
to wait. As a bonus, you can get up to
$15,000 with a qualified purchase from
Preserve Gold. So don't wait. Text Dr.
Phil to
50505. That's Dr. Phill to
today. Before 911, we had literally zero
uh penetrations of al-Qaeda. In fact,
several months before 9/11, I was
entertaining a group of Middle Eastern
uh intelligence officers at
headquarters. This was something that we
did literally every single day. We would
have these delegations of visitors from
our partners around the world. We would
give them a day full of briefings. We
would exchange gifts, take them up to
the director's office for a photo op,
and then we take them out to a nice
dinner afterwards. We would do this with
different groups every single day. And
so I had scheduled an al-Qaeda briefing
for this delegation. This was July the
6th, 2001. I still remember the date.
And I asked the junior al-Qaeda analyst
just come in, give these guys just the
basic briefing. Instead of the junior
analyst coming, the director of the
CIA's counterterrorism center,
Ambassador Kofer Black, showed up with
the chief of operations for the Osama
bin Laden unit. And I I stood up and I
said, "Oh, gentlemen." And I said, "This
is Ambassador Kofheer Black. He's the
director of of counterterrorism." And
and Kofheer sat down and said,
"Something terrible is going to happen.
We don't know what it is. We don't know
where it'll be, but we know it's going
to be an attack on a massive scale." He
said, "We're hearing code words for an
enormous attack. The honey salesman is
coming with vast quantities of honey.
There's going to be a great football
match. There's going to be a a huge
wedding. We're hearing al-Qaeda camp
commanders on the phone with their
students and they're crying and telling
their students, "I'll see you in
paradise." He said, "I'm begging you if
you have any sources inside al-Qaeda.
Please help us." And at the end of the
day, I went to his office to thank him
for taking the time to come and speak to
these men. And I said, "Ker, I have to
ask you. I don't work on al-Qaeda. Were
you saying that for their benefit or
were you serious? And he said, "Oh, I
was deadly serious. Something terrible
is going to happen." And then sure
enough, 9/11 came and it played out in
front of us. This meeting was for what
purpose? Why was he there giving this
information? because we were so
desperate to to penetrate al-Qaeda and
we had no uh no operations or cases that
were entrained to lead us to a
penetration. And he believed that an
attack was nearly upon us that he
thought, well, I'm going to throw a Hail
Mary and just ask these random Middle
Eastern intelligence officers if they
have anybody inside al-Qaeda that we
don't know about. Maybe they can help
us. And they couldn't. Nobody could.
They didn't know or they weren't
willing.
They didn't know. Al-Qaeda really wasn't
their problem. Uh al-Qaeda had no no
problem, no beef with with this service.
the, you know, we caught so many
al-Qaeda people in these operations in
Pakistan that I headed after 9/11 that
and they all told the same story that
that they actually made it quite plain
for me. Um, at at the the grunt level,
I'm talking about the 18year-olds, the
19year-olds, right? They all told
basically the same story. They were they
were illiterate. They lived in isolated
villages in their home countries and
they wanted to get married. But what man
would want his daughter to marry someone
who can't read and write, who has no job
prospects, no skills of any kind? So the
local imam went to them and said, "You
don't want to stay in this village. You
should go to Afghanistan and make jihad
against the Americans, and we'll give
you $300 a month, and if you're martyed,
we'll give your parents $500 as a
martyrdom bonus." Well, they couldn't
find the United States on a map. But
$300 is better than no dollars. And so
they made their way to Afghanistan to
fight the Americans at a higher level,
the camp commanders, the al-Qaeda
leadership. It really all started well
for two reasons. One, because we
established military bases in Saudi
Arabia. That's what Osama bin Laden
objected to personally. But for many of
the other al-Qaeda leaders, it was
because we we were so staunchly pro-
Israel in our foreign policy that they
saw this as a way to get back at us to
to pay us back for turning our backs in
their view on on
poor Arabs. That's a different take than
a lot of people hear. So this was a
retaliation and these al Qaeda that were
going into Afghanistan to fight, they
had no beef with America, they were just
going there for the job. They were just
going there for the job. In fact, when I
first arrived in Pakistan in January of
2002, the very first counterterrorist
raid that I led on a on what we believed
to be an al-Qaeda safe house led us to
capture two 18-year-olds from Tunisia.
And as soon as we broke down the door,
they both burst into tears. And one of
them asked if he could call his mom. And
I remember turning to a colleague of
mine and saying, "This is the fearsome
al-Qaeda. This is what we've been so
afraid of. These are
children." And so I just kind of filed
it. We would do raid after raid after
raid. And sometimes we would catch more
important people. Like I said, camp
commanders uh were the the first
significant captures that we had made.
But these guys, like I say,
illiterate, had no idea what the United
States was about, where it was located,
couldn't name who the president was.
This was just a way to earn some money.
Yeah. And when you recruited some of
these terrorist informants, they had to
be high enough up that they knew
something to be of value, right? Yes.
Correct. These weren't the 18-year-old
grunts. These were people that were high
enough up to do some planning and that
sort of thing. Did you have any
guidelines with how you recruited them,
what you could do and not do? No. And
that that is one of the things that I
like to lecture about at colleges and
universities. There were no guidelines.
I mean certainly there would be
financial guidelines. 95% of the
recruitments that a CIA operations
officer makes are for money. It's all
about the money. And it can be $1,000 a
month. It can be $20,000 a month. It can
be a lump sum for $10 million. We can
pay it in diamonds or gold or any way
that you want to receive it. But there
was no guideline as to what to do
ethically or morally. One of the
examples that I use in in speeches when
I go to universities is I say let's say
you are a CIA operations officer and
you've recruited a bonafide terrorist a
member of ISIS or Hezbollah or al-Qaeda
it doesn't matter what it is and this
man has given you actionable
intelligence that you have used to
disrupt attacks and to save American
lives and then you fly out to the Middle
East one month to meet him and he says
to
I've given you everything that you've
wanted. Tonight, you're going to do
something for me. You're going to go out
and you're going to get me a prostitute.
And if you don't, I'm not going to talk
to you anymore. So, I say, "Give me a
show of hands. How many of you would get
give him the prostitute?" And usually
about 80% put their hands up in the air.
And I say, "Yeah, in real life, you
probably would get him the prostitute.
It's not very nice. It's a kind of a
dirty business, but this is the this is
the job that we've chosen for ourselves.
But what if he asks you for a child
prostitute? And people get nervous.
They'll look around. About 10% will put
their hand up and I say,
"Absolutely not. Not under any
circumstances. It's a child for God's
sake." But the issue here is that there
are no rules. Remember, your job while
overseas is to break the law. Your job
is to convince people to commit
espionage for you. Your job is to get
people to give you classified
information or protected information.
It's not to to it's not to disrupt human
trafficking. But you have to go into
this situation with your own set of
moral values. You have to know what the
right thing to do is because
headquarters isn't going to tell you.
They're not going to say, "Oh, remember
uh employee rule number 305 says you
can't provide child
prostitutes." You have to know in your
heart what's right and what's wrong.
But that's up to you. That's up to the
individual. So, if you've got somebody
that just doesn't have a real good moral
compass, they just don't find true north
on their compass and they want that
information, they're going to do
whatever they need to do to get it.
That's exactly right. And sometimes
there are there are employees who can't
turn it off. You know, every 10 years or
so you'll see in the Washington Post or
the New York Times that a CIA employee
almost always an operations officer has
been arrested for sexual assault or for
embezzlement or something like that
because they just don't have a moral
compass. I remember one of my uh station
chiefs telling me early on in my career,
never lie to security, finance, or
medical. They're the three offices that
could ruin your life. Well, it's
actually more than that. Never lie to
yourself. Never lie to your station
chief, right? You've got to bounce ideas
off of somebody to give you a second
opinion. Because if somehow you wake up
one morning and you think it's all right
to put a roofy in in a woman's drink at
a cocktail party and assault her
afterwards, which has happened, then you
need somebody to to check your thought
process. You kind of have the same
process. Whether you're recruiting
somebody for the agency or you're
recruiting somebody that's an enemy
asset, you kind of follow the same
procedure, right? Yes. You spot them,
you assess them, you assess their
vulnerabilities, you develop a
relationship, and then you ultimately
recruit them. It's the same procedure
whether you're doing it for the agency
or you're recruiting some terrorist that
you want to give you secrets. That's
exactly right.
That's exactly right. When you say
assess their vulnerabilities, what are
you looking for? Vulnerabilities are
probably the most important. And they're
not necessarily as awful as they might
seem. A vulnerability may be that a
person, you know, is a drunk or is a
drug addict or or hates his boss and is
is angry for being uh passed over for
promotion. But more commonly, a
vulnerability is this guy really loves
his children and he doesn't make very
much money. And at the CIA, we can get
your child enrolled in any university in
America, quite literally any university
in America, and the CIA will pay for it.
So if you want your child to go to
Harvard or Stanford or one guy asked
Strayer College, we'll do it.
Um, another vulnerability is uh somebody
who just really loves the United States.
I recruited a an agent one time who
would not take a single dollar from me
and didn't want any favors like a
college education for his children or
grandchildren. He just loved the United
States and he enjoyed the excitement,
the clandestinity of uh of meeting um
and then you know sometimes you'll get
somebody whose spouse has cancer or some
dread disease and by God you can get
them into the Mayo Clinic or the
Cleveland Clinic and and they'll give
you anything that you want so long as
you can you can provide medical care. So
that's what you're assessing in that in
that development. uh stage or the
assessment and development stage. What
can I give this person that is going to
make him want to give me what I want?
And how do you get them into the
university? How do you get them into say
Harvard or University of Texas or
wherever? How does the CIA do that? The
CIA has agreements with
uh just well every university almost
every university in America uh with
every you know Fortune 1000 or Fortune
1500 uh company in America and you know
university administrators and corporate
leaders they're they're patriots as well
and they want to do whatever they can to
be helpful. I I'll give you another
example. I I recruited a guy who was
absolutely crazy for the Chicago Bulls
and I got him a basketball autographed
by Michael Jordan. I just bought it at
at the, you know, the NBA store online
and had it shipped out to me. And I told
him, "Listen, you know, I know a guy who
knows a guy who knows Michael Jordan.
And we told Michael Jordan all about
you." and he autographed this basketball
and I put it in this acrylic box. He
couldn't give me the information I
wanted fast enough and he didn't take
any money for it. It was just because I
was so thoughtful, he said that I gave
him this basketball because I knew how
much he loved the Chicago Bulls. So, you
find what their currency is, what
they're interested in, and then you find
a way to get it to them. That's exactly
right. And money is not a particular
barrier when you're going after somebody
that the agency values.
No, no. I I'm smiling because we used to
have this saying that intelligence is a
cash business and cash is not a problem.
uh you know during during the
Afghanistan war in the very early days
of the Afghanistan war we were literally
throwing money out of the side of
helicopters and it led to this joke at
the agency that you can't buy an Afghan
warlord but you can certainly rent one
and that's what the agency did. So, if
they get a million dollars to rent a
warlord and it's cash, how do you know
they didn't rent them for 750 and keep
250? That is a great question and I will
tell you over the course of my entire
career, I never saw or heard of anybody
taking a single dollar. Again, we're
doing this out of a sense of patriotism
and duty. Now, when you're meeting with
a with a source and you give him his
monthly pay, which of course is always
in cash, he signs a receipt and the
receipt, it's perfectly fine if he signs
Mickey Mouse. He never signs his real
name. You tell him just pick a name,
stick with that name, and uh you know,
that's what he signs every month. Uh but
you're going to be polygraphed on this,
too. And they're going to ask you, have
you ever misappropriated uh funds? I
think the question is, have you ever
misappropriated more than $20? That's
what they asked me on the polygraph. And
by God, you have to be able to say no.
And you have to be able to say it with a
clear conscience. So, they do check. Oh,
yeah. In fact, Dr. Phil, I remember uh
when we had a colleague of mine and I
were setting out to um to drive to
Fiselabad, Pakistan. This was about two
weeks before we captured Abu Zuba. And
we had um $2 million in cash in the van
with us in two duffel bags. And my
colleague said, "You know, I could never
understand why people would cheat on
their on their accounting paperwork for
for 20 bucks or 30 bucks. What would
possess you to cheat the the CIA out of
20 bucks? If you're going to steal,
steal millions." And we looked at each
other and laughed. And I said, "Yeah, I
I wouldn't even steal the millions." And
he said, "No, neither would I." Yeah.
It'd be a little hard to pass a
polygraph on that, right? That's right.
But it's not unfathomable for a
highlevel source. I know in Zero Dark
30, they have a scene in there and
they're trying to get a source to come
up with a phone number and he wants a
Lamborghini. So, they just get him a
Lamborghini in the middle of the night.
That's not far-fetched.
No. No. That's actually easy. You just
take a big sack of money over to the
Lamborghini dealership by the airport
and next thing you know you've got a
Lamborghini. Yes. He's happy and you got
the phone number you want or the
information you want and moving on.
Exactly. Right. All it's all in the name
of the of the successful operation. All
of it. Yeah. I remember just after 911
uh I I went up to Ambassador Black and I
said, "Keoffer, I wanted to talk to you
if you have a minute. I have an idea for
an operation." And before I could get
the words out of my mouth, he put his
hands up and he said, "Whatever it is,
just do it. I have so much money, I
can't possibly spend it all." And that
that continued for years after the 9/11
attacks.
Really? And where did that money come
from? Congress couldn't appropriate it
fast enough. Um, we were we were
receiving multibillion dollar
supplemental appropriations. So we had
our our fixed budget that that the
oversight committees had or the
appropriations committee had
appropriated and the oversight
committees had authorized and then
literally the day after 9/11 we got
something like 160% supplemental uh
appropriation and then got another one
again at the end of the year. We really
couldn't spend it all. And you had no
problem with that. to you that's
business and you're doing what you have
to do to get what you need to get. When
was the first time you became aware of
and had a problem with I guess we'll
call
them enhanced interrogation techniques.
I had an inkling when I was still in
Pakistan. Uh we we captured so many
al-Qaeda fighters on the night of the
Abu Zuvea capture that we had to bring
them into our safe house for
interrogation in shifts in a patty
wagon. And the first group of 10 came
out of the patty wagon and they were all
wearing hoods. And I said to one of the
one of my colleagues, he was working for
me. I said, "Why why are they hooded?"
And he said, "We don't want them to see
our faces." And I I got angry and I
said, "Are you seriously telling me that
you have never read the Geneva
Convention? It is a war crime to put
hoods on them. Take the hoods off." And
he said, "Stop. Don't take the hoods
off." And I said, "I'm going to report
you to to headquarters." And he said,
"I'm going to report you to
headquarters." I said, "Fine." And I
took the hoods off and we reported each
other to headquarters. And I was
reprimanded. So, I thought, "Wow, well,
the Geneva Convention is crystal clear
that hooding a prisoner is a war crime.
I guess it's a new world. I'm going to
have to get used to it." But then I got
back from Pakistan in May of 2002 and I
was standing in the in the sandwich line
at the CIA cafeteria and a senior
officer walked up to me very casually
and he said, "Hey, I'm glad I ran into
you. would you be interested in being
trained in the use of enhanced
interrogation techniques? I had never
heard that term before. And I
said,"Enhanced interrogation techniques?
What's that mean?" And he said very
seriously, he said, "We're going to
start getting rough with these guys."
And I said, "Well, what does that mean?"
And he described these 10 techniques.
And I said, "That sounds like a torture
program." And he said, "No, it's not
torture. The Justice Department approved
it and the president signed off on it. I
said, "Uh, give me an hour. I I need an
hour to think about it." So, I I just
walked out of the cafeteria. I went up
to the seventh floor of the CIA, which
was the executive floor. There was an
extraordinarily senior officer up there
for whom I had worked in the Middle East
10 years earlier. And I knocked on his
door and I said, I said, "Hey, I need
some advice. Uh, I was just asked if I
want to be trained in these enhanced
interrogation techniques. what do you
think of that? And he said, first of
all, let's call a spade a spade. He
said, this is a torture program, and
torture is a slippery slope. And you
know how these guys are. Somebody's
going to go overboard and they're going
to kill a prisoner. And when that
happens, there's going to be a
congressional investigation, and there's
going to be a Justice Department
investigation and somebody's going to go
to prison. Do you want to go to prison?
And I said, "No, I don't want to go to
prison." So, I went back downstairs and
I said, "Look, I have an ethical and
moral problem with this and I think it's
illegal. I'm not interested." And I'm
sorry to tell you that of the 14 people
that were approached, I was the only one
who said no. And so, I I had a friend in
the counterterrorism center who he
happens to be a psychiatrist and a
brigadier general, and we go to the same
church. We're in the same men's group.
and he came up to me uh a few days later
and he said, 'You know they're calling
you the human rights guy behind your
back. I said, 'Ye, I know. I've heard
it. And he said, 'You know that's not a
compliment, right? And I said, Steve, I
don't care. I'm on the right side of
this and they are not, and I'm sticking
with my guns. What were some of the 10
on the list? Well, it started off with a
few that were very mild. I I would not
consider to be torture where, you know,
you grab somebody by the lapels and give
them a shake and say, "Answer my
questions, dog on you." Um, and then it
graduated to a smack on the belly. It
was called an attention slap cuz it
leaves a handprint. It makes a loud
cracking sound. Then it was a slap in
the face, but but it graduated to things
like um water boarding where the
prisoner is strapped down uh on a board.
His feet are elevated compared to his
his head. U cloth is put in his mouth
and then water is poured on his face and
it's supposed to induce a feeling of of
drowning. In fact, in the case of Abu
Zabeta, he did drown and had to be
revived uh because too much water had
gotten down his throat and his heart
stopped beating. But then there were a
couple of other things that I believed
were worse than uh water boarding. One
was called the cold cell where a
prisoner was stripped naked. He was
chained to an eyebolt in the ceiling
like this. His cell was chilled to 50°
F. And then every hour a CIA officer
would go into the cell and throw a
bucket of ice water on him. And we we
murdered several prisoners that way. Uh
they they died of hypothermia. There was
another one um that sounds like it's no
big deal, but it was sleep
deprivation. So again, you're stripped
naked, chained to that eyebolt in the
ceiling, so you can't kneel or lay or
get comfortable in any way. um loud acid
rock music is is uh is uh pumped into
the cell. These industrial strength
lights are on 24 hours a day. Well, we
know that this is according to the
American Psychological Association, the
APA, that people begin to lose their
minds around day seven with no sleep.
They begin to die around day nine, die
of organ failure. But the CIA was
authorized to keep people awake for up
to 12 days and people died because of
that uh that technique as well. So I
said, "Listen, you know, this this is so
clearly illegal." I had done some
research on my own. We we have a law in
this country called the Federal Torture
Act of 1946, which specifically outlawed
exactly those techniques that the CIA
was now using. And in fact, we executed
Japanese soldiers who had waterboarded
American PS during the Second World War.
Furthermore, in January of 1968, the
Washington Post ran a front page
photograph of an American soldier
waterboarding a North Vietnamese
prisoner. On the day that that picture
was published, Secretary of Defense
Robert McNamera ordered an
investigation. The soldier was arrested.
He was convicted of torture and
sentenced to 20 years at
Levvenworth. And then like magic in 2002
all these things are suddenly legal.
Well, we never we never amended the law.
The law never changed. We changed. We
took on this this air of victimhood that
because we were the good guys and we
lost 3,000 civilians on September 11th
that it was okay for us to do this
because we had to stop this existential
threat that al-Qaeda had become. And
once you became aware of all this going
on, how did you become a whistleblower?
How did you actually do it? Only very
reluctantly. And I'll tell you, I wish
that I could tell you that I stood up
and I told them, you know, that's not
the way it happened at all. This was
clearly illegal in my view. So, I waited
for somebody who was directly involved
in the torture uh to come forward and go
public. I actually got promoted on the
strength of the Abu Zubeta capture and I
I was promoted to become the uh
executive assistant to the CIA's deputy
director for operations. So in that
position, it's such a stressful position
that you can only do it for a year. You
know, you're in the office at 3:45 a.m.
You're briefing the deputy director at
6:00. You brief the director at 7. So
it's it's tough. Uh, but it also gave me
access to literally everything that the
CIA was doing around the world for that
one year. And so I'm following this
enhanced interrogation situation at a
secret prison overseas. And um, I kept
waiting for somebody to to come uh
forward and and blow the whistle on it
because people were writing in
classified channels, hey, I'm a I'm a
medical doctor. I took a hypocratic
oath. This is not what I signed up for.
I'm not doing this. I quit. I want to
come back to headquarters. So, there
were, you know, dozens of people
objecting to this program. I thought
certainly somebody's going to say
something and nobody did. Finally, I
resigned
um to go into the the private sector. I
wasn't making enough money to put five
kids through college. So, I had to I had
to do something different.
And two and a half years after I
resigned, I got a call from Brian Ross
at ABC News. I had never spoken to a
journalist before. So I didn't know
about these journalist tricks. But he
said that he had a source who said that
I had uh I had tortured Abu Zubeda. I
said absolutely untrue. I was the only
person who was kind to Abu Zubeda. I
said I never laid a hand on Abu Zubeda
or on any other prisoner. your your
source is either grossly misinformed or
he's a liar. And like I said, I didn't
know these reporters tricks. And Brian
Ross said, "Well, you're welcome to come
on the show and defend yourself." I
said, "Uh, yeah, I'll think about it." A
couple of days later, President George
W. Bush is giving a press conference.
And he looked right in the camera and he
said, "We do not torture like that." And
I said to my wife, who was also a senior
CIA officer, I said, "He is looking the
American people in the eye and he's
lying to them." And then two days later,
it was a Friday and the president had
walked out of the South Portico of the
White House. He was walking to the
helicopter to go to uh Camp David and a
reporter shouted a question about
torture. And the president stopped and
turned and said, "Well, if there is
torture, it's becau it's because of a
rogue CIA officer." And I told my wife,
"Brian Ross's source is at the White
House and they're going to try to pin
this on me." So I called Brian Ross and
I said, "I'll do your show." And I
decided in the four or five days, you
know, between that call and the show
that no matter what he asked me, I was
going to tell the truth and let the
cards fall where they may. And that's
how it happened. So you went on ABC News
interview. You said what you said about
what was going on and clearly stated you
didn't involve yourself in torture. You
were recruited. You were asked to do it,
declined.
Correct. But you didn't deny that it was
going on. Correct. I said three things
that that
that caused the controversy. I said that
the CIA was torturing prisoners. I said
that prisoners were
um that um I'm sorry, CIA was torturing
its prisoners. That that torture was
official US government policy. There was
no rogue CIA officer. and I said that
the policy had been personally approved
by the president. And here's where it
gets
weird. A, as you might expect, the the
CIA uh filed what's called a crimes
report against me with the FBI, saying
that I had revealed classified
information to the public. So, the FBI
investigated me from December of 2007 to
December of 2008. And then in December
of 2008, they they sent my attorneys a
declination letter declining to
prosecute me. They said
that Human Rights Watch, Amnesty
International, and the International
Committee of the Red Cross, Red Cross
had all published papers saying that the
CIA was torturing its prisoners, that it
was the worst kept secret in Washington.
So, they declined to prosecute. My wife
and I actually went out to dinner that
night to celebrate.
And then three weeks later, Barack Obama
becomes president and he names John
Brennan as the deputy national security
adviser for counterterrorism. John and I
always disliked each other. I never
trusted him. I never liked him. And he
was one of the godfathers of the torture
program. All of a sudden, he's
pretending to be whatever he is, a
Democrat. I don't know.
I had no idea that within days of
Obama's inauguration, John Brennan asked
the Justice Department to secretly
reopen the case against me. And so for
the next three years, my phones were
tapped, my emails were intercepted, and
teams of FBI agents um followed me
everywhere I went, even into church. We
learn later we we received 15,000 pages
of discovery after I was charged. I was
charged in January of of 2012 with five
felonies including three counts of
espionage. And remember espionage can be
a death penalty charge and I had three
counts. So, we we learned in
Discovery that Brendan had written a
memo to Eric Holder, the attorney
general, and he said, "Charge him with
espionage." And Eric Holder wrote back
and said, "My people don't think he
committed espionage." And then Brennan
wrote back and said, "Charge him anyway
and make him defend himself." And so
they did. And then 10 months later, I
went bankrupt under the weight of $1.15
million in legal fees. And as soon as I
went bankrupt, they dropped the
espionage charges. Well, didn't Brennan
concede in writing that there was
absence of any evidentiary foundation
for the charge?
He sure did. And you know, I'm I'm proud
to say that as terrible an experience as
this was, as difficult an experience as
this was, not just for me, but for my
wife and my children,
um I knew I was right. And
so what they ended up doing was because
there there was no I hadn't leaked any
classified information. They
found an email exchange that I had with
an author. An author reached out to me
saying he was writing a book on the Abu
Omar rendition. Abu Omar was a Muslim
cleric in Milan, Italy, and the CIA
kidnapped him and sent him to Egypt. And
he was tortured in Egypt. And then the
Egyptians came back to us and said,
"This is the wrong guy. We don't know
who this guy is. We're just going to let
him go." So, he was writing a book about
this operation. And he wrote to me to
ask if I could introduce him to uh to
somebody who knew the Abu Omar case. And
I said I said, "Listen, kidnapping
wasn't my thing at the agency. I don't
know anybody who was involved in this
case." So, he sent me a list of a dozen
names. He said, "Can you introduce me to
any of these people?" I said, "I don't
know who any of these people are." He
sent me a second email with another
dozen names. And I told him, "You
obviously know this case better than I
do. I only know what I've read in the
Washington Post." And he said, "Well, in
your first book on page whatever it was,
165, you talk about this guy,
John. Can you introduce me to him?" And
I said, "John? Oh, yeah." I said,
"You're talking about John Doe." I said,
"I don't know what ever happened to him.
He's probably retired and living in
Virginia
somewhere. That was a
felony. That was a violation of the
Intelligence Identities Protection Act
of
1982. Now, that law had only been
invoked once for a spy, a woman, a CIA
secretary who was sleeping with a member
of the Ganaan Intelligence Service. And
she gave him the names of all of the
recruited agents in Ghana. and the
government executed them. The law was
never again used uh against anybody
until me. And because they couldn't get
me on espionage, they said, "Well, we'll
get him on this." And the Justice
Department said, "Well, wait a minute.
He didn't actually expose the name. He
just confirmed the
name." And Brennan said, "Run with it."
And so they did. In the end, my wife and
I, well, I got a what the Justice
Department called the best and final
offer of uh 23 months. See if this
description is right. After the ABC News
interview, Keryaku exchanged emails with
a freelance writer. In the emails, he
disclosed the name of a former CIA
colleague who had participated in the
detention and interrogation program. The
employee at the time was at the time
still undercover. The freelance writer
then shared the name with the lawyers
representing detainees held at
Guantanamo Bay. The name then appeared
in a sealed legal filing submitted by
the defense attorneys. Although the name
was not made public at the time, the
disclosure angered federal officials and
the resulting federal investigation led
to Keryaku's arrest. The name that was
disclosed appeared on the New York Times
website in October of 2011.
So, what they're saying here in this
account is that the name that you
confirmed was only disclosed in sealed
legal filings and was not made public at
the time that you didn't make the name
public.
No, no, I didn't make the name public.
And you know, one of the things that
really stung at the time was while I was
going through this whole ordeal awaiting
trial, the director of the CIA, um, uh,
General, uh, David Petraeus, revealed
the names of 10 undercover CIA
operatives to his girlfriend and
biographer.
Yet he was charged with a misdemeanor,
one sole misdemeanor, and he got 18
months of unsupervised probation. And at
his sentencing hearing, the judge came
down from the bench to shake his hand
and thank him for his service to the
country. Absurd, isn't it? Well, it
certainly sounds like a very personal
vendetta.
I mean, clearly a double standard and a
targeting. But let me ask you
this. Do you
think in the final analysis that the
things that
you disclosed and wrote about
weakened this country or strengthened
this country?
Oh, I think they weakened us. Seriously
weakened us. You know, we really are
what Ronald Reagan once called a shining
city on a hill for so much of the world.
They want to look up to us. They love
that Congress has mandated uh a human
rights report every single year for
every country in the world with which we
have diplomatic relations. They want us
to be leaders on human rights. They want
us to take the high road. they they
respect us because of it. So, getting
down into the mud, John McCain said
something uh at the time, uh John
McCain, of course, the the senator from
uh Arizona and the former Republican
presidential nominee, he said, "Never
get into a fight with a pig. You're both
going to get dirty, but the pig enjoys
it." And truer words were never spoken.
You know, I was in prison for 23 months
and six weeks before I was released, I
called my wife. I I was allowed to call
my wife every other day for 15 minutes.
So, I called her and I said, "How was
your day?" And she said, "It was great."
And I said, "Great? Really? What made it
so great?" And she said, "The Senate
torture report came out today and it
proved that everything you said was
true." and she said, "John McCain got up
on the floor of the Senate and said that
the country owed you a debt of gratitude
because the American people would
otherwise not have known what the
country was doing in their name." And
you know what? That made it all
worthwhile. Certainly, over the course
of 23 months in prison, and I was in
real prison, I wasn't in some club fed.
I would sit there and feel sorry for
myself, but that single event made it
all worthwhile. And then thank God uh
just weeks later we saw passage of the
McCain Feinstein amendment which
formally and permanently banned torture.
So I I'm I'm proud to have had whatever
role I had in that legislation. This is
something we should never have done. It
made us weaker as a country. It turned
people around the world against us. It
didn't make us any safer.
It it was just wrong from the very
beginning. Well, I can tell you having
been trained in both clinical and
forensic psychology and having spent a
lot of my professional career in
deception detection, interrogation
techniques, and you know, of course,
deception detection has two pieces to
it. One is determining when someone is
lying, and then the other part is
getting to what is the truth. That's
right. And those are two very separate
things. One is is somebody telling you a
lie? And then if they are, then what is
the actual truth with torture
or enhanced interrogation techniques,
they almost always lead to some kind of
information.
Absolutely true. Not
necessarily truthful information or
useful information. And it always
require that you go to a higher level of
interrogation the next time to get a
piece of information. It's not nearly as
effective
as psychological techniques and
relationship building. Other times there
interrogation techniques and they are
manipulative. There's no question. It's
psychological warfare.
Everything from planting a mind virus
to
doing different things to manipulate the
person's thinking
and plant false hope and do various
types of mind games. But the research is
very clear. You're going to get further
faster with psychological interrogation
techniques than you do with physical
torture. That's not a close call, is it?
No, it's not a close call. We We can all
complain about the FBI as much as we
want, but if there's one thing that the
FBI is really good at, it's
interrogations. And at the secret prison
after uh Abu Zuba uh recovered from his
gunshot wounds, he was interrogated by
an FBI agent by the name of Ali Sufan.
And Ali was a master at interrogations.
He treated Abu Zuba with respect. He
would give him a cup of tea, give him an
orange, uh later on a a sheet of paper
and a pen to write to his parents. He
built a relationship. He built a rapport
with Abu Zuba to the point where Abu
Zubeda trusted him and volunteered
actionable intelligence that saved
American lives. That's the way to do it.
Well, I think that all negotiators and
interrogators will tell you one of the
key tenants of building a rapport is the
individual has to believe that you
understand why they're doing what
they're doing. And until unless and
until they believe you get it, that you
understand why they're doing what
they're doing, you're never going to get
past first base. But once they believe
that you get it, that you understand why
they're doing what they're doing, only
then will you begin to have any kind of
rapport with any kind of exchange of
information. Unless they believe that,
hey, he or she understands why I've done
this action or taken this position, they
feel like they're just talking to a
suit, an empty suit. They just feel like
they're just talking to a machine. I I'm
I'm with you 100%. I I made one
recruitment that I was very proud of. Uh
he was a member of al-Qaeda relatively
well a mid-level member of al-Qaeda. And
when I was leaving Pakistan to return to
the United States, I asked him, "Why did
you allow me to recruit
you?" And he said, "I've been here for 5
years and you were the first person that
ever asked me about my children." And
that's all it was. It was that I was
kind to him.
nothing more. Yeah. What mattered to
him. I totally get it. Well, John, we're
out of time for today. I would like to
talk again and pursue some more of the
information that we haven't gotten to,
but I think is so very very important
and interesting to people to understand
what is really going on. I want people
to learn more about what you have to
say. You know, John is a best-selling
author of The Reluctant Spy and doing
time like a spy. He is a champion for
human rights and transparency. John, I
hope we can talk again and do a part two
of what we're talking about today
because I'd love it. I'm not a third of
the way through my outline of what I
want to talk to you
about, but I could talk for this much
time again. If you would allow me, I'd
like to reschedu and pick this up for
part two because I think people will be
absolutely compelled because we're just
starting to scratch the surface here.
Well, thank you so much. I'm a very
longtime fan and this was a real treat
for me. Thank you so much for having me.
I look forward to the next time. It has
been for me. We'll do this sooner rather
than later and we'll just kind of pick
up where we left off. Can we do that?
I'd love it. Thank you. It's been an
absolute pleasure. Very intriguing
conversation. We'll talk again very
soon. Thank you so much. Thank you, Dr.
Phil. All right. Talk soon.